Guide to the Gramercy Neighborhood Associates Records 1828–2009 (bulk, 1912–2009) PR 370
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Images, 1828–2000
  - Subseries IV.A. Photographs and prints, 1828–2000
    - Fourth Avenue (Park Avenue South), circa 1863–1949 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      Views of Fourth Avenue (later renamed Park Avenue South) between Union Square and East 32nd Street, including the Clarendon Hotel (219 Fourth Avenue); 250 Fourth Avenue (under construction); New Amsterdam Hotel (265 Fourth Avenue); All Souls Unitarian Church (southeast corner of East 20th Street); St. Paul's Methodist Episcopal Church (at East 22nd Street); Fourth Avenue Presbyterian Church (at East 22nd Street); Young Men's Christian Association Building (at East 23rd Street); Episcopal Church Missions House (281 Fourth Avenue); original Metropolitan Life Insurance Company building (at East 23rd Street); Tiffany Glass and Decorating Company (at East 25th Street); railroad depot (at East 27th Street); Peter Cooper's home (at East 28th Street); A. T. Stewart's Hotel for Working Women (at East 32nd Street).
    - Fourth Avenue (Park Avenue South) [oversize], 1891, undated (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 4)
      Views of Calvary Church (277 Fourth Avenue), the United Charities Building (287 Fourth Avenue / 105 East 22nd Street), and All Souls Unitarian Church (391 Fourth Avenue).
    - Broadway, 1980s (Box 6, Folder 21)
      Views of demolition work for the site now occupied by One Union Square South (a.k.a. 842 Broadway and 142 Fourth Avenue) and Church of the Puritans (southwest corner of Broadway and East 15th Street).
    - Madison Avenue, circa 1870–1980s (Box 6, Folder 22)
      Views of the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company Tower (1 Madison Avenue) under construction, and looking northwest from East 55th Street.
    - Madison Avenue [oversize], 1950s (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 5)
      Rendering of the New York Life Insurance Company Building (51 Madison Avenue).
    - Fifth Avenue, 1840s–1902 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      Views of the South Dutch Church (corner of 21st Street); the Flatiron Building (175 Fifth Avenue) under construction; and St. Patrick's Cathedral (between East 50th and 51st Streets).
    - Fifth Avenue [oversize], 1860s (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 6)
      Engraving (likely from Harper's Weekly) of St. Patrick's Cathedral under construction.
    - Madison Square, 1896–circa 1925 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      Aerial views of Madison Square Park and vicinity
    - Madison Square [oversize], circa 1900 (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 7)
      Turn of the 20th century bird's-eye view of Madison Square Park and surrounding architecture.
    - Union Square, 1828–1900 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      Views of Union Square Park, its statuary, and surrounding architecture.
    - Washington Square, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
      An apparently mid-19th century engraving of "Washington Parade Grounds."
    - Aerial views, 1855, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 27)
      Aerial views of the vicinity of Gramercy Park as seen from the Latting Observatory (West 42nd Street between Fifth and Sixth Avenues) and from the Metropolitan Life Tower (1 Madison Avenue).
    - Aerial views [oversize], 1907 (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 8)
      Aerial view of the vicinity of Gramercy Park from the Metropolitan Life Tower (1 Madison Avenue).
    - Unidentified location, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
      Interior view of an unidentified church.
    - People, 1879–1974 (Box 6, Folder 29)
      Photographs of Edmond T. Quinn's medallion of Samuel B. Ruggles; Augustus Saint-Gaudens's relief of Richard Watson Gilder with his wife, Helena De Kay, and son, Rodman; members of the National Arts Club and Gramercy Neighborhood Associates caroling at Christmas, 1974; and an unidentifed man writing at a desk (possibly John B. Pine, author of The Story of Gramercy Park, 1831–1921?).
    - Negatives, 1919, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
      Negatives for a number of prints found throughout Subseries IV.A.
  - Subseries IV.B. Stereoviews [15], circa 1853–1888
    Filed alphabetically in two categories: stereoviews of New York City, and stereoviews of Washington, D.C.
    - Stereoviews of New York City [13 views], circa 1853–1888 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      • Congregational Church of the Puritans (Union Square West) & Spingler House (undated)
      • Free Academy, New York (undated)
      • Free Academy, 23d Street, N.Y. (undated)
      • Park Avenue, N.Y. [Church of the Covenant, Park Avenue & East 35th Street, 1863–5]
      • St. Bartholomew's Church (Madison Avenue & East 44th Street) (undated)
      • St. Bartholomew's Church (Madison Avenue & East 44th Street), entrance (undated)
      • St. Patrick's Cathedral, interior (1888)
      • St. Patrick's Cathedral, rear view from Park Avenue (undated) [2 copies]
      • St. Stephen's Church, interior (1853–1865)
      • Union Square Hotel (undated)
      • Young Men's Christian Association (23rd Street and 4th Avenue), Lecture Hall (undated)
      • Young Men's Christian Association (23rd Street and 4th Avenue), view from (undated)
    - Stereoviews of Washington, D.C. [2 views], 1869, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
      • Corcoran Art Gallery, Corner seventeenth street and Pennsylvania Avenue (undated)
      • Smithsonian Institution (1869)
  - Subseries IV.C. Postcards [46], circa 1900–1980s
    Filed alphabetically in three categories: postcards of Gramercy Park and vicinity, postcards of New York City, and postcards of elsewhere.
    - Postcards of Gramercy Park and vicinity [19 cards], circa 1900–1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      • Gramery Park South / Consolidated Edison Bldg.—14th St.
      • Hotel Gramercy Park, 21st Street at Lexington Ave, New York
      • Hotel Irving, Twenty-six Gramercy Park, New York City
      • Landmarks of New York City [Gramercy Park]
      • New York's famous Gramercy Park, East 20th to 21st St., off 4th Ave.
      • The Players [3]
      • Statue of Edwin Booth [2]
      • View Over Gramercy Park [2]
      • Washington Irving House
      • West Gate, Gramercy Park [3]
      • Three World War I era postcard-size poems by "RWH": "To A.S.T." (September 29, 1918); "A Prayer for Peace" (October 1, 1917); and "In Gramercy Park" (December 25, 1918).
    - Postcards of New York City [18 cards], circa 1907–1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      • Flatiron Building [1]
      • Grace Church [2]
      • Madison Square Garden [1]
      • Metropolitan Life Insurance Company Building [3]
      • Old College of the City of New York [1]
      • Old Grand Central Depot, 42nd Street [1]
      • Reception Room, Y.M.C.A., 23rd St., N.Y. City [1]
      • St. Patrick's Cathedral [4]
      • Union Square [3]
      • Washington Square [1]
    - Postcards of elsewhere [10 cards], 1962–1980s (Box 7, Folder 5)
      • Ringwood Manor, Ringwood State Park, Passaic County, New Jersey [9]
      • Sunnyside, Tarrytown, New York [interior]
- Series V. Print matter, 1894–2009
  Books, pamphlets, and periodicals pertaining to Gramercy Park proper, the surrounding neighborhood, its notable residents, and architectural features.
  - Subseries V.A. Books and pamphlets, 1894–2002
    Filed alphabetically by author or title.
    - Academy of Music [program], [1907] (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Week beginning Monday evening, March 4, 1907. Klaw & Erlanger's production of Gen. Lew Wallace's "Ben-Hur" under the direction of Joseph Brooks.
    - [Academy of Music]. Souvenir Book with the Program of the ceremonies attending the closing of the Academy of Music on the Seventeenth of May Nineteen Hundred and Twenty-six, 1926 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - [Bank for Savings]. History of the Bank for Savings in the City of New York, 1819–1929 by Charles E. Knowles, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - [Bank for Savings]. Some Historical Notes of the Early Days of the Bank for Savings in the City of New York, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Before the Red Cross, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Brooks, Gladys. Gramercy Park: Memories of a New York Girlhood, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Carmer, Carl. The Years of Grace, 1808–1958 [Grace Church] (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Cohen, Paul E. and Robert T. Augustyn. Manhattan in Maps, 1527–1995, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Cohen, Paula. Gramercy Park: A Novel, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Garmey, Stephen. Gramercy Park: An Illustrated History of a New York Neighborhood, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      Related Materials
      See Box 3, Folder 11, for promotional material for Garmey's book.
    - Gilder, Rosamond, ed. Letters of Richard Watson Gilder, 1916 (Box 9, Volume 1)
      Richard Watson Gilder (1844–1909) was an American poet and editor of "The Century Magazine" and a resident of No. 24 Gramercy Park.
    - Gramercy Park's Illustrated Bulletin. This issue is dedicated to the New York World's Fair, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Guide to Gramercy Park and Environs [2 versions], 1955 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Historic Hudson Valley. Visions of Washington Irving: Selected Works from the Collections of Historic Hudson Valley, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Klein, Carole. Gramercy Park: An American Bloomsbury, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Klein, Carole. Glories of the Gramercy Park Area: A Walking Tour [3 copies], 1991 May (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Kress, S. H. and Company. Old New York, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Kring, Walter Donald. Henry Whitney Bellows, 1979 (Box 9, Volume 2)
      Henry Whitney Bellows (1814–1882) was an American clergyman, and the planner and president of the United States Sanitary Commission, the leading soldiers' aid society, during the American Civil War.
    - MacCraken, Henry Noble. The Family on Gramercy Park, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Maurice, Arthur B. "Literary Landmarks of New York," The Mentor, vol. 8, no. 15 (serial no. 211), 1920 September 15 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Mendelsohn, Joyce. Touring the Flatiron. Walks in Four Historic Neighborhoods: Madison Square, Gramercy Park, Ladies' Mile, Chelsea, 1998, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Merwin, Samuel. My Favorite Club [The Players], 1933 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Morgan, Charles H. George Bellows, Painter of America, 1965 (Box 9, Volume 3)
      Artist George W. Bellows (1882–1925) lived at 146 East 19th Street.
    - Municipal Art Society. Adopt-a-Mural. A program concerned with the fate of New York City's Public Murals..., [1990–1993] (Box 8, Folder 21)
      Contains an article on the Barry Faulkner murals installed at Washington Irving High School in 1921.
    - Museum of the City of New York. Gotham Comes of Age: New York Through the Lens of the Byron Company, 1892–1942, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Old Buildings of New York City, With Some Notes Regarding Their Origin and Occupants, 1907 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Pine, John B. The Story of Gramercy Park, 1831–1921 (Box 8, Folder 24)
      See Box 2, Folder 16, for an advertisement and promotional material for Pine's book.
    - Scheffel-Halle [Scheffel Hall, 190 Third Avenue] (photocopy), circa 1904 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Shaw, Charles G. New York—Oddly Enough, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Shepp, James W. and Daniel B. Shepp. Shepp's New York City Illustrated, 1894 (Box 9, Volume 4)
    - Thompson, Victoria. Murder on Gramercy Park: A Gaslight Mystery, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Underhill, Lydia, and Elisabeth Holden Webb. In Gramercy Park, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Zeisloft, E. Idell. The New Metropolis: Memorable Events of Three Centuries, 1600–1900, 1899 (Box 9, Volume 5)
  - Subseries V.B. Periodicals, 1954–2009
    Titles beginning with "Gramercy" are filed chronologically, followed by the New York Chronicle.
    - Gramercy Graphic [14 folders], 1954–1967 (Box 10, Folder 1–14)
      • 1954: Summer [2 copies], October-December
      • 1955: January-December
      • 1956: January-December
      • 1957: January-December
      • 1958: February, March [2 copies], May [2 copies], June [2 copies], Midsummer [2 copies], September [2 copies], November, December [2 copies]
      • 1959: January [2 copies], February, March, April, May [2 copies], June-July, October, November, December
      • 1960: January, February, March [2 copies], April, May, June, September, October [4 copies], November, December
      • 1961: January, February, March, April, May-June [2 copies], Summer, September, October, November [2 copies], December
      • 1962: January, February [2 copies], March-April, May, June, Summer, September, October, November, December [2 copies]
      • 1963: January [2 copies], February [2 copies], March, April, May-June [2 copies], Summer, September, October, November [2 copies], December [2 copies]
      • 1964: January, February, March, April [2 copies], May, Summer, September, October, November, December
      • 1965: January-December
      • 1966: January-December
      • 1967: January-March
    - Gramercy Herald (newspaper), 1970–1985 (Box 10, Folder 15)
      • 1970: October 1
      • 1971: March 5
      • 1973: April 27, May 4
      • 1976: April 30, July 2 (Bicentennial supplement)
      • 1985: January 18 (title = "The Community Herald")
    - Gramercy Neighborhood News, 1988–1990 (Box 10, Folder 16)
      • 1988: Autumn
      • 1989: Fall–1990: Spring
      • 1990: Autumn
    - Gramercy: The Newsletter for the Gramercy Neighborhood [3 folders], 1991–1993 (Box 10, Folder 17–19)
      • 1991: Spring, Fall
      • 1992: Spring [3 copies], Fall [2 copies]
      • 1993: Spring [2 copies]
    - Gramercy Neighborhood Associates, 1997 May (Box 10, Folder 20)
      • 1997: May [3 copies]
    - Gramercy Gazette [13 folders], 1997–2009 (Box 10, Folder 21–33)
      • 1997: July [3 copies], October [3 copies], November [4 copies]
      • 1998: March [2 copies], September [2 copies], November [3 copies]
      • 1999: October, November [3 copies]
      • 2000: March [2 copies], Holiday [2 copies]
      • 2001: Spring [2 copies]
      • 2002: Spring [4 copies], Fall [4 copies], December
      • 2003: Spring, Fall
      • 2004: Winter [2 copies], Spring [2 copies], Fall [2 copies]
      • 2005: Winter [2 copies], Spring, Fall, December [called "GNA Membership 2006"]
      • 2006: Winter, Spring, Fall
      • 2007: Winter, Spring
      • 2008: Winter, Spring
      • 2009: Winter, Spring
    - New York Chronicle [10 folders], 1987–1999 (Box 10, Folder 34–43)
      Many issues carry contributions by longtime Gramercy Neighborhood Associates archivist Stephen Garmey.
      • Vol. 2: no. 1 (Summer 1987), no. 4 (1988)
      • Vol. 3: no. 1 (1988), no. 3 (Spring/Summer 1989)
      • Vol. 4: no. 1 (Winter 1990), no. 2 (Spring/Summer 1990), no. 3 (Fall 1990) [2 copies], no. 4 (Winter/Spring 1991)
      • Vol. 5: no. 3 (Spring/Summer 1992), no. 4 (Fall/Winter 1992)
      • Vol. 6: no. 1 (Spring 1993), no. 2 (Summer 1993), no. 3 (Fall/Winter 1993), no. 4 (Spring 1994)
      • Vol. 7: no. 1 (Summer 1994), no. 2 (Fall 1994), no. 3 (Winter 1995), no. 4 (Spring 1995)
      • Vol. 8: no. 1 (Summer 1995), no. 2 (Fall/Winter 1995), no. 3 (Winter 1996), no. 4 (Spring 1996)
      • Vol. 9: no. 1 (Summer 1996), no. 2 (Fall 1996), no. 3 (Winter 1997), no. 4 (Spring/Summer 1997)
      • Vol. 10: no. 1 (Fall/Winter 1997), no. 2 (Spring 1998), no. 3 (Summer 1998), no. 4 (Fall 1998)
      • Vol. 11: no. 1 (Winter 1999), no. 2 (Spring 1999) [4 copies]
- Series VI. Maps, 1831–1953, undated
  Original and reproduction maps of Gramercy Park and vicinity.
  - Edwin Smith, surveyor. Map of the Park laid out by S. B. Ruggles in the City of New York, with sixty six surrounding Lots, 1831 December 1 (Folder Oversize 2)
  - [Map of Gramercy Farm, drawn for Samuel B. Ruggles], 1831 (Folder Oversize 2)
  - J. B. Holmes, surveyor. Stuyvesant Property known as the "Petersfield Farm," Together with the adjoining properties formerly owned by C.T. Williams, Tompkins & Dunham, Thos. H. Smith and Others., 1866 September (Folder Oversize 2)
  - John B. Holmes, surveyor. Map of Rose Hill Farm, Gramercy seat, and the Estate of John Watts, 1866 November (Folder Oversize 2)
  - Places to know in the Gramercy-Stuyvesant area of New York City (Gramercy Graphic picture map) [8 copies], 1953 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Places to know in the Gramercy-Stuyvesant area of New York City (Gramercy Graphic picture map) [8 copies], undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Map reproductions, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    • Map of James Duane's land, measured in acres, rods, and perches (1763 November 5)
    • Map of the six acres James Duane bought from John Watts Jr. to complete Gramercy Farm (1786)
    • Map of Gramercy Farm, drawn for Samuel B. Ruggles (1831)
    • Edwin Smith, surveyor. Map of the Lower Division of the Lands of Samuel B. Ruggles in the Twelfth Ward of the City of New York (1831 December 31)
    • Egbert Ludovicus Viele. Sanitary & Topographical Map of the city and island of New York [detail] (1864/65)
    • John B. Holmes, surveyor. Map of Rose Hill Farm, Gramercy seat, and the Estate of John Watts (1866 November)
    • "Gramercy Park as of 1852" from Kenneth Holcomb Dunshee's As You Pass By (1952)
    • Zoning map of the Gramercy Park neighborhood showing residence, business, and unrestricted districts.
- Series VII. Material from the Trustees of Gramercy Park and Gramercy Neighborhood Associates, 1831–1956
  Some of the items here were received on loan or deposit from the Trustees of Gramercy Park and/or the Gramercy Neighborhood Associates (then called the Gramercy Park Association) in 1949. For details, see the notes inside Box 11.
  - Gramercy Park deeds, titles, map, etc., 1831–1956 (Box 11)
    • Map of the Park laid out by S. B. Ruggles in the City of New York, with sixty six surrounding Lots. New York, Decr. 1st, 1831. Edwin Smith, City Surveyor. [negative no. 63275] 1831 December 1
    • Samuel B. Ruggles and Mary R. Ruggles, his wife, to Charles Augustus Davis and others, Trustees. Deed of Gramercy Park. 1831 December 17
    • Samuel B. Rugges & Mary R. Ruggles, his wife, to Charles Augustus Davis, Thomas L. Wells, Robert D. Weeks, Thomas R. Mercein, Philo T. Ruggles, and Others. Confirmatory deed of the Park. [N-YHS negative no. 63272–74]
    • Thomas L. Wells, Philo T. Ruggles, and others, to Norman White, James W. Gerard, and William S. Johnson. Deed to change Trustees of Gramercy Park. 1843 August 5
    • William S. Johnson, Robert D. Weeks, Norman White of the first part; Alexr. M. Lawrence, Eben E. Crocker & Charles P. Kirkland of the second part; Cyrus W. Field, Horace Brooks & others of the third part; and James W. Gerard and Charles A. Davis of the fourth part. Deed to change Trustees of Gramercy Park. 1854 February 6 [oversize]
    • Alexander M. Lawrence and Charles P. Kirkland, 1st part; Curtis Judson, Robert T. Woodward and Samuel J. Tilden, 2nd part; Cyrus W. Field, Courtland Palmer Jr. and such other persons, owners, etc., 3rd part. Deed to change Trustees of Gramercy Park. 1874 March 4
    • Alexander M. Lawrence and Charles P. Kirkland, to Samuel J. Tilden and others, Trustees. Deed. 1874 March 20
    • Samuel J. Tilden & Curtis Judson, 1st part; Cyrus W. Filed, Jonas Henry Lane, & Edward B. Wesley, 2nd part; Clarkson N. Potter, Henrietta B. Haines & others, 3rd part; Deed to change Trustees of Gramercy Park. 1877 April 21
    • Abstract of Title of the Trustees of Gramercy Park. 1886 February
    • Gramercy Park. Entrance Keys to the Park for present season are now ready for delivery... [printed]
    • The taxes and assessments on Gramercy Park for the year 190–, and the expenses of collecting the same... [printed]
    • Gramercy Park. At a meeting of the Board of Trustees of Gramercy Park held on the 28th day of December, 1904, the following resolution was passed... [printed]
    • Resolution passed by the Trustees of Gramercy Park... [printed]
    • New York, 194– To the Trustees of Gramercy Park... [printed]
    • Gramercy Park. Rules... [printed]
    • Gramercy Park. Application for a key for the year Oct. 1, 194– to Oct. 1, 194–... [printed]
    • Trustees of Gramercy Park. New York, Dear Sir: The Trustees of Gramercy Park have been referred to you by Mr.... [printed]
    • Trustees of Gramercy Park [blank stationery]
    • Trustees of Gramercy Park [blank envelope]
    • Gramercy Graphic: February 1941, November 1949 [4 copies], December 1949, May 1956